A Guide to the Blue Ridge Library Records, 1920-1933
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Blue Ridge Library Records 1920-1933
Thomas Balch Library
SC 0073
This collection consists of cancelled checks, bank statements, letters, bills, receipts, and other monetary records of the Blue Ridge Library, dating from 1920 to 1933. The checks are signed by Mrs. Mary E. Dillon (ca. 1886-n.d.), Mrs. A.C. Norman (ca. 1895-1988), and Mrs. Lillian Dillon (1874-n.d.), who were treasurers of the library respectively from 1920-1933. The bank statements record library funds deposited in and withdrawn from the Purcellville National Bank from 1920-1932. The letters include correspondence from library president Mrs. Alice P. James (1887-1946) concerning funds from a bazaar that the library hosted, correspondence with the Literary Guild of America, and correspondence with the cashier of the Purcellville National Bank. The bills are for subscriptions to the Ladies' Home Journal.
Purcellville Public Library, Purcellville, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Purcellville Public Library, Purcellville, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
1991.0004
Historical Information
The Blue Ridge Library began around 1885 in the Purcellville jewelry shop of Joseph R. Janney (1842-1911), local jeweler and retired Civil War soldier. Janney had collected about four shelves of books that he would loan out to Loudoun County citizens for a few cents apiece. In 1899, the library was taken over by Lillian Davis (n.d.), Virginia B. Hirst (1857-n.d.), Linda Pancoast (ca. 1878-n.d.), and Mary Virginia Smith (n.d.), who organized a collection of 407 books in the general merchandise store of Mr. W. P. Pancoast (1852-1940). On 23 May 1900, however, a fire began in Pancoast's store which spread quickly and destroyed the entire central portion of Purcellville. It is unclear how much, if any, of the collection was saved from the flames. After the fire, the library moved around to various locations, including a dentist's office.
The Blue Ridge Library was run by a board of executive officers, and it hosted fund-raising events such as plays, concerts, and other entertainment. In order to encourage the inhabitants of Purcellville to make use of the library, it also held a weekly story time for children. The library was privately funded during this time, and in 1934 a committee was selected to appeal to the town council for public funds to pay the library's rent.
Records suggest that the Blue Ridge Library closed down at some point between 1934 and 1936 due to the Depression. In 1936, however, the Blue Ridge Library board elected to build a new building for a Purcellville Public Library and Community Center. Funds came from benefit concerts and shows and a grant from the Federal Public Works Administration, and the new library was completed on 13 September 1937. The Purcellville Library still exists today as part of the Loudoun County Public Library System.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of cancelled checks, bank statements, letters, bills, receipts, and other monetary records of the Blue Ridge Library, dating from 1920 to 1933. The checks are signed by Mrs. Mary E. Dillon (ca. 1886-n.d.), Mrs. A.C. Norman (ca. 1895-1988), and Mrs. Lillian Dillon (1874-n.d.), who were treasurers of the library respectively from 1920-1933. The bank statements record library funds deposited in and withdrawn from the Purcellville National Bank from 1920-1932. The letters include correspondence from library president Mrs. Alice P. James (1887-1946) concerning funds from a bazaar that the library hosted, correspondence with the Literary Guild of America, and correspondence with the cashier of the Purcellville National Bank. The bills are for subscriptions to the Ladies' Home Journal.
Arrangement
Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, United States Census, United States Census and Voter Lists. http://www.ancestrylibrary.com (accessed 10 June 2011).
Loudoun Cemetery Database. http://www.leesburgva.gov/index.aspx?page=940 (accessed 10 June 2011).
Marsh, Helen Hirst. Purcellville, VA, 1852-1952. Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Scheel, Eugene. The Story of Purcellville. Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Washington Post, 24 May 1900.
Washington Post, 29 August 1920.
Washington Post, 20 May 1934.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Purcellville Library and Bookmobile (SC 0081), Leesburg, VA.
Contents List
- Cancelled checks Oct 1920-June 1921
- Cancelled checks June 1922-Sep 1923
- Cancelled checks Nov 1927-July 1929
- Cancelled checks Aug 1929-Jan 1933
- Bank statements 1920-1927
- Bank statements 1928-1930
- Bank statements 1931-1932
- Correspondence
- Ledgers
- Bills
- Receipts